[SPEAKER_00]: These questions seem to revolve around a sūtra that maybe I should read out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the sūtra, the Bhikkhuni Samhita, from the nun Bhajira, and talk about the chariot.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if it is enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mara, the evil one, says, by whom is this creature formed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is the creature's maker?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is the risen creature?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is the creature that ceases?
[SPEAKER_00]: And Vajra, the nun, says, why do you refer to the creature, Mara?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you involved in wrong view?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a pile of pure determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is here no creature to be found.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as for an assemblage of parts there is the term a chariot, so when there are the aggregates, convention says a creature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is merely suffering that comes into being, suffering that stands and disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing apart from suffering comes into being, nothing other than suffering ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's quite good.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that's the whole point there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The designation of a chariot.
[SPEAKER_01]: As she says, can I have that, this one, please?
[SPEAKER_01]: She never... she does not deny the name, the film, given to the assemblage of parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an assemblage of parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a name chariot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a functional assemblage of parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called chariot.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assemblage of parts, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can break the chariot into parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, you can discern the parts within the chariot.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can discern more particular things within the general things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimately, the most general being the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of form, feeling, perception, determinations, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that general phenomenon,
[SPEAKER_01]: of those aggregates, you can have more particular manifestations of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the experience as a whole of all of it, you can call a person, you can call whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's a difference between if you're just designating it, or if that designation stands for your self-view, for your wrong view of really assuming the priority of that designation over those parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is, like, the questions of the King... King Milinda, I think it revolves around similar, but that's like... it's somewhat subtle, but not that subtle, but again, if people don't read it carefully, they won't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by... he dismisses.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says that by destroying parts, you destroy the name that you've given to the parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or... not even that, not even you destroy, but more like you deny the reality of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he said, well, see, there is a chariot, but if you take a chariot and break it up, break these parts up, then there is no chariot anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's still parts of chariot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just it's not functional anymore, so you can call it somewhere else, something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't... like, he might have replaced a particular designation of a chariot, but he doesn't see that he did not undo the nature of designation standing for your wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, he might have fixed... well, not even fixed, he might have replaced or affected a particular designation, but not affected the nature of designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can destroy the chariot into parts, into... or even destroy the parts into completely non-functional parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, there is a designation in regard to that you would call a pile of rubbish.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's equally real, as the chariot was a designation for a functional assemblage of those parts, not just when they were thrown around in a pile.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't, like, even conceive not having a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, name and matter, nāma, rūpa, are just all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just, oh, undo nāma and have the pure rūpa or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even think in those terms, but they do imply
[SPEAKER_01]: that affecting designation, destroying it, denying its reality, or whatever else, somehow frees you from the view attached to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't, because you can't actually even conceive the absence of designation, because an absence of designation is another designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there is no designation here.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just designated it with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Sister Vajira here, she does not
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhuni Samyukta, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: She does not... yeah, Vajira Dhanan.
[SPEAKER_01]: She does not deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: She doesn't say this chariot is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: She says, this chariot, this designation exists on account of the five aggregates existing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But she has fully understood that the five aggregates have arisen on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot even conceive being a master of them or owning them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that reason, they will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, any designation that arises in regard to that, shares the same nature, cannot even be owned, appropriated, accessed, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just designates this while this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this is not anymore, that designation is it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's no question of whether it's real or not, and what's behind it, and what comes first, nor anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, she has no need to destroy the five aggregates to prove to herself that designation is mere hollow designation or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: She knows that the five aggregates have... You can't even destroy the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's incomprehensible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't change the order of the parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: As Aniruddha points out in his critique of the questions of King Melinda, because you can undo chariot, but you can't do your own experience and, like, throw it on a pile and prove yourself that your designations, because of that, are not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a fantasy that doesn't even stand, like, remotely for the way things actually are, because you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive to step outside of your experience and change it to see that it can be changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's what happens when people want to observe.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to perceive the change as a proof of impermanence or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as I said before, that's not what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impermanence is in the fact that a thing, an aggregate, a phenomenon of any kind, has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say in its manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that very reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it has a reason, that's why it has to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: No other reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it manifested,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no access to the point of origin of that manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive how things are... Well, they just manifest, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can discern is arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that reason, that thing will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: But can't you also... you can... you can discern the arising, but you can also know that it is dependent, that it has arisen because of some... Well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Dependent on something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't arise... you can't just have designation and no rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just talking about the experience as a whole now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not just talking about...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not talking about designation itself here, when I was referring to anything that arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because anything that arises can be taken as a thing itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the Sotāpanna's insight, whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be it the designation, be it the perception, be it this, be it that, shares the nature of arising, because it partakes in that nature, for that reason, because it manifests, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you see it's ending, you see it's cessation, you see it's disappearance or destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know that it's there, because it has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it hasn't a reason, it could have not ceased in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could not be liable to a possibility to cease in the future
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was manifested, that's why it's gonna go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you never see it go, you know it's manifested, thus it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when I say it's manifested, thus it's impermanent, because, eh... it is dependent on something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also... What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like the five aggregates, I feel, feeling comes to be by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they all come fine, but still, what's the dependence?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see the connection there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless... unless... go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I mean, like, if there is dependence on the other four.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, but the other fours are equally dependent then on each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: On each other, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which means that you basically, from an arisen thing, that has arisen, you went into comparison with other arisen things, and now you treat them as a group, failing to see that that entire group is just one arisen thing also.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a more general level, and that is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: For no other reason than the reason of... because it has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, you can get five audience, you can say they are... well, they depend on each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, on what all five of them depend then?
[SPEAKER_01]: On nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any dependence you look of that kind is a linear dependence that you can perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't need to depend on anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the fact that they have manifested, and that your sense of self comes secondary to that, and always will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't exit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be the reason for the manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm here, and then create them out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even the thought of I'm here is already preceded by the appearance of the five Ascetics.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they're always ahead of you, or below you, or in front of you, or around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're enclosed within them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be the most accurate way to put it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, yeah, there is no feeling without perception and intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an intention without feeling and perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, depending on what approach you take, the point is, well, all of them, as the experience as a whole, as general as you can push it, share the same nature of being manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the sole reason for their impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't explain that using linear explanations, because if you could,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that our view could be explained, could be deduced by observing things, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so subtle to get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a view, but it comes only personally as a direct insight, based on, obviously, external instructions, knowing what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's always summed up in that general, very general
[SPEAKER_01]: Description of whatever has a nature arising, has a nature ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is basically the other word putting it, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has a nature arising, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your five aggregates don't cease for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you need them to actually observe their cessation in order to understand impermanence, that's a constriction in terms of means, because you'll be dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they cease...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you observe impermanence then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, impermanence is not in the sub... in the scientific observation of... of things disintegrating.
[SPEAKER_01]: The impermanence is in the fact that you have no control, no input in that very subtle, very general notion of things arising, manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the experience of destruction of things, it's another arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, changing whilst ascending is also manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because things manifest, they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because they have a duration or a shelf life.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always a sun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe I can't remember far back enough, or it's... things are always changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always things just taking on different forms, never-ending, just taking on another form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Evolving, becoming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I am...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember
[SPEAKER_00]: Our previous life or previous forms...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a durationless happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you fail to see, right there and then, that you have a thought that connects all of those forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not seeing that thought as impermanent, which is where your Self is, which is why there are wrong views, which is why people can't think that, and which is why people do think, ah, like, the matter,
[SPEAKER_01]: The four great elements of five, depending on what division you take.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's, like, listeners' wrong views in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing really destroyed, nothing really changes, they're always there, they just change its shape or whatever else, but it's always the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has been, always will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you chop someone's head off or whatever, it's just elements going through elements, nothing exists, nothing happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that that is a very gratuitous thought, a view that you adopted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no proof for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you can't remember what was in your previous life, how can you remember that it was there, if you can't remember that it wasn't?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you decide, because it's more pleasing to you, for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You decide that there was.
[SPEAKER_01]: You decide that there will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to remove all of the bad faith, which means it takes away all of the wrong views, the only fact
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing that you can refer to it almost as a fact, as a law, as something that is undeniable, as something that you did not create, that you did not concoct in your thoughts or assumptions, would be whatever has a reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the whole dhamma is built just on that, or within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, you can build pretty far.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you look back to the memories of your past, you connect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make that connection right here, right now, for which you have no proof anymore than the fact that you don't have proof whether it was really always changing or not, or impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know, which means you decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make an assumption that it was so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I was... like you have a photo of yourself as a child, and you, as a teenager, then you make the connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at the photo and say, that's who I was.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's who I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is a connection, in a sense that there is a connection between particular and general.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is still the enduring body that is changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a one-off shoot from your mother,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is now growing old and aging and so on, while overall remaining the same body, the same projects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's just... there's just things existing on different levels of generality.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are particular changes that are allowed to, because on a more general level, the thing remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, arising, ceasing, and changing while standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not all linear in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if you approach your designation in that sense, you won't see it as a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will always be in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eh... Can you, eh... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that is a problem, because... things need to exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, things' existence is comprised on different levels of generality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: A more particular change means on a more general level it's not changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if you look at general level, you can see it's changing there, because on a more general level it's not changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the ultimately not changing on the most general level?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the nature of form, nature of feeling, nature of perception, nature of determination, nature of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the five aggregates will always remain that which is in common
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can think, ah, so the five obligates are myself then, because that remains unchanging.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That changes too.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nature, in regard to that, remains the same, because there is a change on a more particular level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Itaniel, or Craig, when he was called, when he was born,
[SPEAKER_01]: People say that's not a... that's not the real thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just... someone's decided to...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why she says, why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the aggregates and the term designating them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is, and it always has been, suffering being arising, suffering ceasing, suffering arising in regards with suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole structure, in general, in particular, it's completely irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I mean, it's relevant in a sense that it's confused as a source of problem, but it's not actually the source of problem, which is why it says, when there are the aggregates, you call it a creature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's merely suffering that comes into being, suffering that stands, and suffering that disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: There has always been an issue, and you fix that, you fixed all of the issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, denying the reality of designation, saying, well, this is just an empty convention, as such, it is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's... what's the problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's empty or full, what's the problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying that it's an empty convention means you just designated further the original convention or designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You designate a creature and now it's an empty designation of a creature.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... and you can go indefinitely like that, infinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people can say...
[SPEAKER_00]: It was never an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things like, uh, I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was African, now I'm British.
[SPEAKER_00]: See?
[SPEAKER_00]: Designations aren't real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is basically all revolves around denying their suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you deny the reality of things that are apparently causing you to suffer, you feel like you dealt with your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a... it's a... well, it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a big mistake from the start, because neither designations nor anything external was ever the reason for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were, freedom from it would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things arise of their own, which means suffering would always be manifested on its own, which means you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, be it a subtle designation, a coarse designation, an empty designation, a full designation, be it a real thing or an unreal thing, all of those are manifest phenomena, and as such, they're external, which means they're never the reason for suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's craving in regard to them, in regard to what you feel, in regard to how you perceive things and so on, that the suffering is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of craving means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of craving is absence of suffering, leaving the whole domain of designations, five aggregates, intact, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because you don't discern that, because a person is patujana, does not see the origin of suffering as a noble truth, he assumes, automatically, and that's what every patujana has in common, you can't do this by accident,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't do it wrongly by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every putujana assumes that when he suffers in regard to something, it's that something that's the reason for his suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can you can sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: On a most... on the crudest level, you'll hate people, or you said something, he's a bad person, because I'm suffering when that comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's utterly, 100% his fault that I suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you might work through that attitude and realize, well, be that as it may, I really don't have say over other people, so you might start refining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't be able to go further than blaming designations for suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Blaming the apparent reality of things for your suffering, which is the ultimate reaching point, which is not really ultimate of any kind, of Mahayana Buddhism or any other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even the contemporary Theravāda Buddhism, which denies the reality of things through Western science, has proven that things are constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, see, it's all an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely mistaken point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mistaken view, mistaken direction, that the only purpose of it is to allow you to keep denying things, so not to suffer immediately on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not freedom from suffering, it's just management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to deny... well, the fact that you need to deny means you're affected first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you need to deal with it, and denial will be a form of dealing with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sotāpāna and then ārad, they don't have to act upon
[SPEAKER_01]: The unpleasant feeling at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't need to do anything on account of unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a reason why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have pulled out the first arrow, so they're not hit by the second arrow of needing to do things when you experience pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, psychotherapy, psychology, contemporary Buddhism, every other religion, are all forms of management of the suffering, because you don't know the escape from it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_01]: Your best recourse of action is to manage it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you manage it to explain anyway, oh, it's my chemical imbalance, that's why I suffer, or, well, it's because, you know, my parents were not supportive of me when I was young, or, oh, well, no, it's because everything is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these are mere conventions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you exist, but you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think pain is real, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those revolve around the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know the way out of this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm just trying to justify it, trying to explain it, blaming it externally, but never really understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were, then, yeah, parents didn't love me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a fact on account of which I have to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are real or unreal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if I... the fact that I can say that things are unreal, that's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That designation is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, their lack of reality might pertain to a more particular level, if you deny that wasn't real.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on a more general level, as a designation that you just uttered, that you were able to think of, that you were able to direct and designate, it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a contradiction in terms of saying, oh, this is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's not real, it just wouldn't be manifested at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be able to even think about it, let alone speak and point at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that confusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes out as a result of not knowing the way of suffering that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing something arisen and then trying to make it not be what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're suffering in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be as if a person is sick, terminally ill, and there is no apparent cure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the end, he just starts denying his illness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not... this life is not real to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he starts dismissing it all, because it alleviates suffering to some degree, through bad faith, through ignoring, through turning a blind eye, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't fix the illness at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't affect it in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just makes you not look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the attitude of not looking is nothing else than an attitude of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ignoring is what a vijja is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I've said it many times before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a metaphysical veil of ignorance that is sort of being uncovered one day, if you were lucky or if you made enough of the right mystical effort or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance is act of bad faith, act of ignoring, act of not acknowledging, act of assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those acts maintain the act of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're fully responsible for the religion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're maintaining it in your daily actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, not on a particular level, or rather, you won't find it, you won't discern it on a particular level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there, but you won't discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to discern it on a more general level, which is where it arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And general level being in regard to the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can say this is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of that statement, the nature of that experience is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifested as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why all these things need to be allowed to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: In their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you not seeing that impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you end up, you know, putting everything else on the top.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have to do is to start discerning impermanence within the thing, in the heart of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they have arisen, not because they're ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the whole thing will sort of, like, you know, like in the cartoons, when you see a knitted jumper, and then a cat just pulls one string, and the whole thing just gets undone, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you get the right one, and you stick to the right one, stick to the right view, it will unravel everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something you want?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but in terms of, like, yeah, the nature of things, there arise... but if you just leave it as that, you say there is... it is impermanent, but you have to do... you have to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just naturally...
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma, as the universal law, as the universal path that has always been there, can be walked, is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not to say that you're already walking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the impermanence is generally in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it weren't, you wouldn't be able to find it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's there, that discernment is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll find that out when you discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, until you discern it, you have to have faith that it's discernible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that you're doing ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you just say, oh, if I just be with things, that's... you're just being with it, but you're not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you can't... like, that's why you need all of these, like, you know, so many suttas and and and and countless numbers of instructions and descriptions and encouragements and pointers and so on that the Buddha was going around teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you just stay with things, well, you're just staying with your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't keep throwing more rubbish onto the thing you're trying to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is just staying with the thing that has a reason, not piling up more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, that's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now that you're with it, now you need to start doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that you learn how not to keep throwing more rubbish on your experience, in terms of the wrong views and so on, you learn that, you get established in that, that's a starting point now, so you can begin a proper work of, you know, taking further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually, people, you would hear, you know, Buddhist monks, satchans, whoever... That's where everything would come in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And every religion teaches that, in one form or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just sort of, either through denying the world or whatever, but you arrive at the point of just being with things, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just let it flow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just let it flow, just be here now, present, aware, in the present moment, just... don't judge, don't do this, don't do that, just be, just be, just be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that, yeah, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that you're just being, you have to start discerning that very just being a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else that you thought the problem was, was just extra, on top of your problem, that was preventing you to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that you learn how to just be mindful and simplify your life, that's, like, before you begin the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not to, like, not to be confused as a final goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's so far from it, that it's just... it's still wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still putrujana, you can still be just present with things,
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't put it in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't put it in your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can spend your whole life... Because ignorance won't... can't get undone by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not there by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to learn how to stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how it's undone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't learn how to stop doing it, you'll just be... you're just being with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the point, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... you, you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not doing itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not fast upon you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is not given to you... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, again, ignorance or whatever, any other wholesome states you want to pick up from the suttas, it's all where that craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, it all shares the nature of that very craving, which is something you're doing in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense that you can say craving is the reason for your suffering, direct reason for suffering, not that on account of which you crave, which results in suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing external is the direct reason for suffering, except your craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can say, ignorance is the reason for suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing external, but your attitude in regard to the external.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude of ignoring, the attitude of turning a blind, the attitude of bad faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the reason for suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was a very distinct answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: This couple in Norway,
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's in Norway.
[SPEAKER_00]: The government said that they need to register a baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: They need to register the baby's name.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they refused to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they were fined.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they were forced to go and register the name for the baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they called it B X J Y Z Z 1 2 3... like it's 21 letters.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I heard that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I heard one.
[SPEAKER_00]: They said, no, it's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to register properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, put A.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they would find it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can't just call it A.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to give it...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they... there's a classic example that they were trying to get away from this whole institution, this whole society, because that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the... they have the cause of... they saw it in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think that's why they suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're not going to let their child go to the same... shun society, shun...
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that shunning the society is another attitude towards the society, which, in this particular case, resulted in even more hassle, for which they felt fully justified in their anger and their will, because I'm sure they thought they were right.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just equally deluded, as the society that is put in the name now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never ever the problem was not the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it's the... it's a very common
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether, as I said, in other schools of Buddhism, or rather all schools of Buddhism today, or other religions, that's the most you can get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deny the reality by one mean or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've mistakenly blamed it from the start, the reason of your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And denying of it removes the apparent reason of your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still are suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's just a management.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's a response to the present suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dealing with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not preventing it to arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... like, you can spend your whole life managing your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of it, you still remain prey to suffering as much as you were in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have not affected a grain of that nature of being prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being liable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you've been doing is managing the actual suffering, or the prospect of actual suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like, you're just going to, like, just ignore as hard as you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the mystical absorption, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or really enjoy the suffering, really get into it, so it's not a problem anymore, because you really want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You force yourself to want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is a secondary attitude, or rather a response, in regard to the fact, yeah, that it has arisen and you were afflicted by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you accept it, reject it, both, accept it and reject it, neither accept it nor reject it, because there's nothing to accept nor reject, all of those will be a form
[SPEAKER_01]: There are forms of response, reaction to the fact that it has arisen and it struck you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fact that you have no option but to respond, but to react, means you're striking yourself a second time on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if one has the understanding of a certifier, that things are not one, or has that understanding of an answer, not self, then what stops him from not doing whatever he wants, whatever
[SPEAKER_00]: You see how it's not mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he abandons responsibility towards things.
[SPEAKER_01]: He overcomes it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a... it's a... it's an experience of liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the burden is laid down.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would compare it to a burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine, as the suttas talk about the jhānas and similar, you were in prison, with your family left out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you worry, because you feel responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're not just, like, they're your family, so you're fully throwing through, taking them as yours, but you're not in control over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're in prison and you worry.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are they going through?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are the bad things going to happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you going to lose them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you going to be killed or raped?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or who knows what?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you go out and you find them intact.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the relief from that burden of that responsibility that you had no input in,
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or crossing the desert, all of those other similes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is, genuinely, feeling like you're laying out a heavy burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... it's a good question.
[SPEAKER_01]: What stops him from doing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing stops him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because he... What stops him is the requirement of sīla being established first, before the dhamma takes place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that was established, when the dhamma took place, and the self-view has been abolished and so on, he can't revert back to those things that were requiring that self-view, which was the unwholesome behaviors.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he sets it up, but then, exactly, he lets go of that as well, which is letting go of sīla, bhātta-paramāsa, letting go of virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's an extreme relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: When
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you lay down your duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You spend the rest of the night just sleeping.
[SPEAKER_00]: But some people say to you, yeah, but what about your mother?
[SPEAKER_00]: She's suffering and you should go and look after her.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're still speaking out of their self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of their sense of duty, they're still burdened by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's making me suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are suffering because of what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do it because it's their personal pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, somebody can misinterpret this and say, oh, okay, so, like, you just start denying everything and say, well, nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can do whatever I want, which is what people do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the order is not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: The order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla comes first, then the dhamma can take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without a sīla, whatever took place, you can be sure that it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and they always say that, the Buddha, when he talks in the suttas, when he would say, then in the center, he understood this, and then the knowledge has been developed,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because his behavior has been purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever he understood then, he understood because, okay, he really made the effort to understand and his behavior has been purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has a sense of shame, fear of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense of shame and fear of wrongdoing and the whole sīla, it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a necessary ground for the dhamma to take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the dhamma does take place, you abandon that ground as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, you know, practicing dhamma, you go beyond good and beyond bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean that that ground gets undone?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, it stays as it... because there always will be a ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: You prepared it and now you took off and that ground is left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously,
[SPEAKER_01]: There are different, you know, different people, different grounds, different level of preparing the ground, different habits, different so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are many different āryas in the suttas, getting up to all sorts of relatively serious mischief.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... which is why that sutta, the Buddha lists things that Sotāpanna cannot do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no mention there that he's not able to break any of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: What satipaṭṭhāna cannot do, what the person who has prepared the ground and then left the ground, laid down the burden, does not care anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't kill the Buddha, kill an arahant, violate the bhikkhuni, kill his mother, kill his father.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't take any determination as permanent, any determination as not suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't take any arisen dhamma as himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't take anybody else
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the things that he can't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can break it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can cheat.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can steal.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can break all the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose, even if he's pushed in some, like, extreme circumstances, he might be able to kill as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that he wouldn't reap the vipakas, the attractions, but it wouldn't be, as the Buddha said, it wouldn't be as bad as the other forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, when you have a little cup of water and you drop one drop of dye, everything is dark, black.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just put black.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you have a hundred liters of water, one drop of dye won't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a drop of dye, a stain, impurity, but because things have changed, that's why he can't be lower than a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't say what kind of human.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if he has been a very misbehaving sodhbhāna, most likely he's going to still be a human, but probably in a very, very bad, bad state, bad position, bad so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, again, somebody with the right view to go to such an extent,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a fear is, if you say that it's not mine, or you have to realize that you become a salesman, but then you have a responsibility to another person, say a child, whatever person,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you fear that if you lose that sense of responsibility, that this... that child will suffer on account of that, because you just... you won't feel it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a fear of losing all sense... sense of shame completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's exactly why these things are a burden, are a yoke.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why
[SPEAKER_01]: Family, friends, duties, responsibilities, they're like pies.
[SPEAKER_01]: They pile you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They obstruct you for their reason, because it's not easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, you need to renounce your own child, your own children, their welfare, their anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to leave the whole thing, yet your success is not guaranteed by doing that, because that's only preparation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's only setting up the ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no guarantee you'll succeed, yet
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to succeed, you do have to leave it completely, utterly, 100% beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they wouldn't, you know, they're like not going, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: They refused in the beginning to teach the householders, because they would understand that, and they would take it on,
[SPEAKER_01]: As, you know, obviously a worth thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will leave, the families.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then go through it and die.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, no man in the house and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would affect lives of many people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they say, okay, well, don't teach it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let them... Like, if they find out and they don't find, but don't be directly responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it will affect other aspects of the order and people and hating and whatever and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the long run, it's better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But still, like, that's just like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: To become an Arahant or something, but there are many Sotāpannas back in the Buddha's day, they were just lay householders.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the Buddha's father came to him, all in tears, upset, distraught, because the Buddha took his grandson, or the Buddha's son, Rahula.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine his state of mind, and then the Buddha calmed him down, and then gave the teaching, and then he understood, and he became a Sotāpanna right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said, okay, well, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do have to go because, you know, we assholes are very busy and so on, so I have things to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna said that upon becoming Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that big a deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in a sense, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in another sense, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's still a lot to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can we see the dhamma by contemplating designation?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is another word for designation?
[SPEAKER_01]: By contemplating that designation is not a problem to begin with, you will learn to allow those more ambiguous, less palpable phenomena, so to speak, such as designations and terms and signs and tokens, to exist, to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not allowing them, you don't see them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, by thinking they are the problem,
[SPEAKER_01]: By denying them, by blaming them, by undoing them, by whatever else people would do, means you wouldn't see them in their nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're not seeing the nature of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're not seeing the nature of arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see the dhamma by learning how not to interfere with the designations and what they designate.
[SPEAKER_01]: By learning how not to main... well, by not maintaining the blame on them for your suffering, but by learning how to leave it as it is, then eventually you'll see where the suffering does come from, which is not them.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you think they're the problem, you'll be trying to fix them, which means you'll be misdirecting your efforts externally, outwardly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not recognizing that the reason for your suffering, as the sister Vajradāna said,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's merely the suffering arising, suffering standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to worry about designations as long as you're not spending your time blaming them for your suffering and saying, well, I'm not real, I don't exist anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: My name, my ethnicity, my nationality, that's all just
[SPEAKER_01]: Empty convention.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, when I experience pain, that's not real either.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a completely gratuitous connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it doesn't free you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's how.
[SPEAKER_00]: The designations cover quite a range of... Nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, nāma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like, there is no just nāma, or there is no just rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything is designated.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even you saw, like, I'm not calling this and you just called it, like, like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to giving any name to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just named it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, name, as in name and matter, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, undoing the name, it's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't undo the name or you can undo the form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not your doing anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Designation is not what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance in regard to it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but to see that nāma, rūpa is not just nāma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, there is not just nāma.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can discern the aspect of nāma in nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can discern the resistance aspect of rūpa in nāmarūpa, but there is not just nāma, just rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and nāmarūpa with another word?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can also be appearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But with wrong view, it exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it says the all, it means everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: From things that are seemingly more material to, like, you know, vague, ambiguous, abstract thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, that's as a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has its matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is right here and then the presence of that living body or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience as a whole, nāmarūpa, remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't even conceive that not being so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Designation is not just a label.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: A label is a designated designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, you labeled it, like intentionally intended something, decided on top of the orderly inclinations that you had.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's a label.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: I call this...
[SPEAKER_01]: I label it as such and such, in such and such regard.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's just like a very proliferated designation, you can say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still shares the same nature of designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you realize the nature of designation, you will realize that labeling was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you abstain from the label, you label it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can't stop choosing, can't stop making decisions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't stop perceiving, you can't stop feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can do is step outside of the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, not step outside, literally, but surmount the whole thing, so you're not affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as the Buddha said, even the Dalai Lama uses designations such as I am, I am this, I was like that, but he does not confuse that designation for his sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not stand anymore for the wrong view of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has cleared that out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now it's a true, just an empty designation, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not empty of everything, empty of its reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's empty of appropriation.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when... so, when a... a sotāpanna says, not mine, he doesn't take that knowledge as his?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, therefore, an arahant, he doesn't say, not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't have to say it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what Kuntījana can't do, he can deny the whole world, say it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what he cannot see as not mine, is he's actually denying the whole world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he can see himself with not-self, he can see not-self with self, he can see self with self, but he can't see not-self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that one again, which is why it's subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter what arises, it's not appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's not his.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he sees not-self, not-other.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees that, not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he needs to persist in it, so the things won't even arise anymore with the offer of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the standing of determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, you can say so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you were... because if you were not able to designate, you'd be dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, there is that sutta, yeah, when it says, if an infant, if the conscience turns away from the name and form, would
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on the list and designation, I've learned a lot about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: With name and matter as condition, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it was said.
[SPEAKER_01]: How it is, Ananda, that with name and matter as condition, there is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It should be seen in this manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: If Ananda consciousness were not to obtain a stay in name and matter, would future arising, coming into a being of birth, aging, death, unpleasure, suffering, be manifest?
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, therefore, that's the reason, that's the occasion, that it's the arising, that this is the condition of consciousness, that's to stay in name and matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus far and under may one be born, or age, or die, or fall, or arise, thus far is there a way of designation, as far as designations can go, thus far there is a way of language, thus far there is a way of description, thus far there is a sphere of understanding, thus far the round proceeds as manifestation in a situation, so far, that is to say, as there is name and matter together with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for other realms, like, yeah, the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They designate, but they might... Yeah, well, the faculties are different, more limited, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they wouldn't have...
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't have the conventional means.
[SPEAKER_01]: The degree of awareness, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But animal, like, they might not be able to speak, but they have that which stands in the form of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sounds they make, the expressions, and it's a form of communication.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more, obviously, cruder,
[SPEAKER_01]: The five aggregates are the five aggregates in any realm, be it the deva realm, or the animal realm, or the hell realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no absence of like, oh, I have only two aggregates, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just five aggregates, the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the composition, the ways of going about, might be different for an animal than a human, which is why animal realm is more unfortunate than human.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's such a perilous realm to be in, animal realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have awareness of your choice, yet you are choosing, and you're fully responsible for the results of that choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So an animal can't help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dog can't help, but chase after things, or hunt things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cat can't help, but kill it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean, oh, it can't help.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not her fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is her fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fire is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a form of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there is not enough awareness for that choice to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they just go with the most obvious inclination that they would have, which is why it's so hard to step outside of the animal realm, because you're just perpetuating the bad action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Action, action fully immersed in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would really need an external circumstances, stroke of luck, to get back from an animal realm, for which you're responsible going to, in the first place, through your bad actions, in other better realms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that stroke of luck is, basically, that that simile of the blind turtle coming up at once 500 years, once every 500 years, to the top of the sea, just for a second, and sticking its head
[SPEAKER_01]: to a yoke that's been floating around and thrown around by winds and waves.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, what are the chances?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, those are the chances of somebody from an animal realm to come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, there is, there is some, like, looking after an animal, helping an animal, feeding it, does, in a sense, like, by making an animal restrain itself,
[SPEAKER_01]: A natural restraint is there in its behavior, and as such, it will count, bit by bit, eventually, in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they don't know... they're not... they're not... they didn't willingly choose that restraint by the fact that restraint was imposed upon them, in a sense of wait before you jump on your foot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means there is a phenomenon of restraint present in their experience right there, right then.
[SPEAKER_01]: A wholesome phenomenon present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Buddha said, in these unwholesome realms, like completely always in darkness, even a tiny little spark of light can mean a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I look after the dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: And cats, and birds, and monkeys...